Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Because today's דף Daf is כ"ז Chaf
Zayin 27, but we pick up on כ"ו עמוד ב', Chaf Vav
Amud Beis, the first two dots, תניא נמי הכי Tanya Nami Hachi
in the
גמרא, Gemara, it's about fifteen lines into the גמרא. Gemara. The line
starts with an asterisk. Okay, so the משנה Mishnah said that before
giving the בכור Bechor to a כהן, Kohen, whether it does or
does not have a מום, Mum, the non-כהן Kohen ישראל Yisrael has
to raise it for thirty days if it's a small animal, fifty
days if it's a cow. We tried to learn it out from
a פסוק, Pasuk, but in the end we sort of said that
the פסוק Pasuk was not explicit, but the rabbis had the latitude
to interpret what exactly was the amount of time. So now we're
going to continue with
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya Nami Hachi, we have similarly: בכור בניך תתן
לי, Bechor banecha titein li,
give me the firstborn of your children; כן תעשה לצאנך, Kein ta’aseh
l’tzonecha, so shall you do for your sheep. So the same way
you only do the פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen after thirty days, you
only give the sheep over to the כהן Kohen after thirty days.
יכול אף לשורך, Yachol af l’shorcha,
maybe even for your ox you give it after thirty days? תלמוד
לומר Talmud Lomar תעשה, Ta’aseh,
you shall do; כן תעשה לשורך ולצאנך, Kein ta’aseh l’shorcha ul’tzonecha,
which means that you shall exert some effort. הוסיף לו הכתוב עשייה
אחרת בשורך, Hosif lo hakatuv asiyah acheres b’shorcha, you have to do
extra effort raising the ox before giving it over to the כהן.
Kohen. Again, presumably it means getting it to a stage where it's
at a certain stage of development, and that requires more time for
an ox. And how do you know exactly that that's fifty days
and the sheep is thirty days? שמסרו הכתוב לחכמים, Shemasro hakatuv l’Chachamim,
that was given over to the sages' discretion to determine what is
the scope of the biblical מצוה Mitzvah and how long you have
to wait until you give it over. And as I said yesterday,
this is an important concept because normally using the hermeneutic principles we
understand what are the parameters of biblical law, but normally there's a
sense that there's like a clear sort of correlation between what the
פסוק Pasuk says and how you derive and what it leads to
the end result. But every now and then the גמרא Gemara says
that actually the פסוק Pasuk is a little open-ended, and what exactly
its parameters are is based on rabbinic discretion. Again, not to make
rabbinic law, but their discretion to interpret the exact parameters of the
biblical law. This is one example which is maybe not the one
that's the most relevant, but I pointed out yesterday two important examples
where it's actually debated: the question of חול המועד Chol HaMoed and
the extra acts of affliction on יום כיפור Yom Kippur in addition
to eating and drinking. That because the גמרא Gemara is ambiguous about
that, whether it's biblical or not, some say it's rabbinic, and I
particularly point to the fact that there are exceptions. And anytime you
have overriding
an exception like a case of loss, we allow you to do
מלאכה Melacha on יום טוב, Yom Tov, or certain types of cases
we allow for let's say a bride or a king to bathe
or wash their face or whatever on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So
that sounds like it's rabbinic, but there's another position of ראשונים Rishonim
that it's דאורייתא, D’Oraisa, but this is given over to the discretion
of the sages, and that allows them even to make exceptions, which
is taking that idea of given over to the discretion of the
sages one step further. It's one thing to say the sages determine
the original parameters, but once those parameters are determined, those are it,
end of story. It's quite another thing to say that because they
determine the parameters they can also say even within biblical law they
can incorporate a certain type numbers of exceptions. But that is definitely
a concept that is used by ראשונים Rishonim a number of times
to try to determine whether something is biblical or rabbinic. I should
say maybe one of the more shocking examples of this is a
position of the יראים, Yera’im, if I remember correctly—I didn't double check—that
says the idea of the ל"ט מלאכות Lamed Tes Melachos on שבת,
Shabbos, you know, which we all say are like learned out from
the משכן Mishkan and so on, but if you actually look at
the list of the ל"ט מלאכות Lamed Tes Melachos on שבת, Shabbos,
they more describe sort of classic types of productive activities. There's a
whole list about the stages that you go through for making bread,
from planting to cutting the wheat to harvesting to making bread; other
stages about making parchment and writing; other stages about clothing. And therefore
there is, I believe, a position of the יראים Yera’im that says
that this is actually not learned directly out from the משכן, Mishkan,
but they actually were given over to the חכמים, Chachamim, their discretion
to determine what are sort of classic acts of productive labor to
determine what are the מלאכות Melachos on שבת. Shabbos. Normally we won't
say that because as soon as you say that, that sort of
discretion and not some type of direct derivative makes people feel a
little less sort of confident about the fact of feeling that it
is biblical. Nevertheless, that is what the גמרא Gemara says, that there
are some times—I'm not extending it to there, but there are some
times where actually what is the parameters of a biblical law is
given over to rabbinic discretion. Yes, Michael?
What I was going to say is very interesting because on the
one hand
what we've been encountering is this concern that if you delay giving
it to the כהן, Kohen, you're going to come to בזויי, Bizuye,
and here we're saying that this whole thing is שמסרו הכתוב לחכמים,
Shemasro hakatuv l’Chachamim, so they could have said you can give it
even after the first day, you would have avoided the whole problem.
Well, that is true. I mean,
but the delaying is not just the delaying of you giving it
to the כהן, Kohen, it's the delaying of even the כהן Kohen
doing anything with it, so you could say, but if you gave
it over, maybe it would— שחט shecht it sooner. Right, but I
think part of the reason why you're supposed to raise it till
this point is because nobody would want to שחט shecht it sooner,
it would be a waste. The idea is you get it to
a point where it's really worth it, you know, to שחט shecht
it. You've got to get some meat on its bones and so
on. So probably it's a good point that there is that other
value expressed before, but presumably the whole reason for the wait is
that you want to wait till, nobody would really שחט shecht it
that soon under normal circumstances. Okay, so let's keep on going.
מכאן אמרו, Mikan amru, from here they said, עד כמה ישראל חייבין
להיטפל בבכור, ad kama Yisrael chayavin lehitepel babechor, how long do you
have to raise the בכור? bechor? בבהמה דקה שלשים יום, Bevehemah dakah
sheloshim yom, grazing animal thirty days. בבהמה גסה חמשים יום, Bevehemah gasah
chamishim yom, large animals, cows, fifty days. רבי יוסי אומר בבהמה דקה
שלשה חדשים. Rabbi Yossi omer bevehemah dakah sheloshah chodashim. No,
grazing animals is three months. Presumably he doesn't disagree with cows. מפני
שטיפולם מרובה, Mipnei shetipulam merubeh,
because it requires a lot of sort of work, a lot attending
to it a great deal, a lot of effort in order to
raise it to a certain stage. Why is that true? תנא, Tana,
we taught in a ברייתא, braita, here's why it requires a lot
of effort for the grazing animals, מפני ששיניהן דקות, mipnei sheshineihen dakot,
because in its early life it has its teeth are not yet
grown in and it's a grazing animal. So without small teeth and
without grown-in teeth, you're going to have to really nurse it, you
know, till it's ready to graze on its own and that effort,
that initial effort is given over to the ישראל, Yisrael, not to
the כהן. Kohen. Okay, everybody who has had small kids knows that
it is those first few months which are the most labor-intensive until
they get to be teenagers. Okay, anyway. So then the
גמרא Gemara goes on.
Okay. אם אמר לו הכהן בתוך הזמן הזה תנהו לי הרי זה
לא יתנו לו. Im amar lo haKohen betoch hazman hazeh tenahu li
harei zeh lo yitnu lo. If the כהן Kohen says within this
time, hey, don't, I'll take it off your hands, give it to
me, don't give it to him. Now, one of the reasons we
mentioned is it could be it gives him an unfair advantage because
then, you know, he'll be, he'll make sure to be the one
who gets it because he's going to take it off your hands.
But the משנה Mishnah goes on to say that if he can
use it immediately, like it's a בעל מום ba'al mum or it's
בזמן שבית המקדש קיים bizman sheBeit HaMikdash kayam and he can bring
it as a קרבן korban immediately, you, he can take it off
your hands earlier if he offers.
So what is the reason there that he cannot if he's not
going to use it immediately? So let's take a look. So מאי
טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason that he can't take it off
your hands if he's not going to use it immediately? So אמר
רב ששת, amar Rav Sheshet, מפני שנראה ככהן המסייע בבית הגרנות. mipnei
shenireh keKohen hamaseya b'veit hageranot.
It looks like the כהן Kohen who's helping you in the threshing
floor. What does that mean? It means let's say a כהן Kohen
comes to you while you're threshing your grain and says, tell you
what, I'll help you thresh your whole grain here for over the
next few days and you agree to give me all of your
תרומה terumah or all of the מעשר. ma'aser. Okay, nice little deal.
Good deal for the ישראל, Yisrael, good deal for the כהן, Kohen,
everybody benefits, win-win. The only problem is is that, you know, it
sort of subverts the whole idea of the תרומה, terumah, which is
supposed to be a free gift to the כהן, Kohen, and it
turns it into just a type of a, you know, a deal
and a payment for services. It's not supposed to be a payment
for services. So you're not allowed to do that. Now, some cases
are not explicitly a deal but are implicitly so or look enough
to be that. So let's say the כהן Kohen says, I'll take
this, this sheep off of your hands. I didn't say it's a
deal, but what is effectively happening? He's getting the sheep, he knows
he's getting it for a בכור, bechor, and what's he doing for
you? He is raising it for the next, you know, 20 days,
right? Because if he's going to שחט shecht it and eat it
immediately or if he's going to bring it to the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash as a קרבן, korban, so then while he saves you
the effort, so you could also say it's a type of deal,
I'm saving you the effort of raising it but you're going to
give it to me, but there's not an exchange of services. Okay,
he just saved you from it, but he didn't do anything for
you. But if he can't eat it for the next 20 days
and he's going to raise it for the 20 days and those
are 20 days you should have been raising him, I'm saying 20
like he took it on day 10, whatever, you know, 30 days,
give him on day one. If he's going to raise it for
the next 30 days and you should have been, it's like he
is raising it for you and in exchange you have given him
the sheep. Okay, so therefore that is much too much like an
exchange of services, like a hire, and therefore we do not allow
it. So it נראה nireh like a כהן מסייע בבית הגרנות. Kohen
maseya b'veit hageranot. It's not exactly that, he didn't say explicitly that's
the deal, okay, but nevertheless it's close, it looks close enough like
you're giving it to him for payment of services.
Yeah, the only reason why you're giving it to him earlier is
so that he doesn't have to deal with it. So I mean,
so it's not like, you know what I mean? I understand, I
understand. So don't, so don't, you know, so don't give him the,
you know, the preferred gift and then he'll, you know, be able
to take it earlier.
I understand,
he was not, he was not necessarily the one who was going
to get it. So he still is, it's, so it's not like
he's just saying, oh, don't bother, because if for example, let's say
it was a כהן Kohen who was a מכירי כהונה. makiri kehuna.
He was the person that was already predetermined you were going to
give it to because you had a whole relationship with him going
back generations and it was known you gave it to him. And
if he therefore said, you know what, don't worry about it, I'll
take care of it, then that's fine. He's just saying don't put
forth the effort. But here there's an exchange because you are choosing
to give it to him and that's the problem. Okay, yeah.
What is the, why, if the כהן Kohen gets it earlier, say
after eight days, whenever he can bring it to a, for it's
going to be sacrificed, why would he have to wait 30 days
for what?
No, he wouldn't. If he has to bring... no, normally the assumption
is is that the ישראל Yisrael will raise it for thirty days
even if he could bring it earlier, because if you bring a
קרבן korban that's a bigger animal, first of all it's a nicer
to God as a קרבן korban and also you get more meat
out of it. Okay, so everybody would like it to be a
little bit bigger before you bring it. All right, but if he
can bring it immediately, then he can take it off your hands.
Although he is, you know, he's getting you out of some work,
he's not there's no exchange of service.
But why couldn't he is what I'm asking. In other words, why
couldn't he bring it after eight days?
He could. But we're talking there's no בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Oh, that's why.
So if there's no בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, then he can't you
cannot take a animal without a blemish, you cannot do this exchange.
But if there is a בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or there is
a blemish, then you can because he could use it immediately. Okay,
so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנן, Tnan, תנו
רבנן. tana rabanan. So now we're going to look at this phenomenon
of כהן מסייע בבית הגרנות Kohen mesayeya beveise hagramos where
he actually pays you to like the value of the swing space.
That might be different. That might be different. No, not he pays
you, you pay him.
Yeah, I mean, that's what I meant.
You pay him. You pay him. Here's the money to raise it
for the next twenty days and I'm also giving this one to
you as a בכור. bechor. Right. The ישראל Yisrael might feel a
little bit cheated out, but okay. Yes, that would be fine. תנו
רבנן, Tana rabanan, we taught. הכהנים והלוים והעניים המסייעים בבית הגרנות. Hakohanim
vehaleviyim veha'aniyim hamesayim beveise hagramos. So it's not only כהנים, Kohanim, there
are a number of people that can would might want to do
this exchange. So it's כהנים Kohanim to get part of the תרומה,
terumah, לוים Leviyim to get the מעשר, ma'aser, עניים aniyim to get
the
מעשר עני ma'aser ani on the third and sixth year.
המסייעים בבית הרועים Hamesayim beveise haro'im that they're helping either with the
shepherds, who would help with the shepherds? The כהנים Kohanim would help
with the shepherds to get the בכור bechor or the זרוע לחיים
וקיבה. zero'a lechayayim vekeiva. ובבית הגרנות Ubeveise hagramos or the threshing house,
ובבית המטבחיים, ubeveise hamitbachayim, actually the בית המטבחיים beise hamitbachayim is זרוע
לחיים וקיבה zero'a lechayayim vekeiva because because the butcher house is the
butcher's the one who gives the זרוע לחיים וקיבה. zero'a lechayayim vekeiva.
So they're helping out. אין נותנין להם תרומה ומעשר בשכרן. Ein nosnin
lahem terumah ma'aser bischaran. So even presumably if you didn't make an
explicit deal, if they're helping out and they're like, 'Yeah, you just
do what you think is appropriate, I'm just here to volunteer my
service.' Okay, so you cannot give them the תרומות terumos and מעשרות
ma'asros as their fee, because otherwise it will either be explicitly or
implicitly a type of using it to pay their fee, a hire
of services. ואם עושים כן חיללו. Ve'im osin kein chillilu. If you
do that, you have desecrated. And not desecrated to the point that
it loses its sanctity or you transgress מעילה, me'ilah, but you have
desecrated the whole institution. Really, as opposed to normally we talk about
desecrating an object, so you've in a sense desecrated the institution of
these תרומות terumos and מעשרות ma'asros which are supposed to be freely
given and here
they're given as an exchange. Why shouldn't poor people help you in
your field and you pay them?
You can. Oh, you can certainly pay them out of pocket. Don't
pay them with the מעשר עני. ma'aser ani.
You can pay them out of pocket, but the מעשר עני ma'aser
ani is supposed to be given to the poor just, you know,
as a free gift.
Yeah, but if you see it, I really I don't understand. If
you let's say you say, 'I'm going to give X amount to
צדקה.' tzedakah. Right. And then you meet a poor person whom you
know is poor. Right. You can't give it to that poor person?
You have to give it to some...
No, you can give it to that poor person, but let's say
for example, let's say I donate to צדקה tzedakah every year, I'm
going to give a thousand dollars to the poor this year. Right.
And then and then I see this poor guy who actually happens
to have some carpentry skills and I say to him, 'You know
what? My house needs some repair. Why don't you come do the
repairs on my house for a thousand dollars?' And then I'll go,
'Oh good, so now I've fulfilled my obligation of giving a thousand
dollars to the poor.'
That's not... That seems to me that's the case here.
That's exactly the case here.
He comes to you, he sees your your painting your your walls
and he says, 'Oh let me help.' Right. He doesn't make a
deal, he says, 'Let me
help.' And then you happen to say, 'Oh, I wanted to give
a thousand dollars, but he's poor, let me give it to him.'
So right, so what you're saying is, so you're right, there are
two cases. There's a real מסייע בבית הגרנות mesayeya beveise hagramos where
there's an explicit deal, which you admit is problematic. And then there's
נראה כמסייע בבית הגרנות nireh kemesayeya beveise hagramos where it's not an
explicit deal, it really was a volunteer and now you're just giving
this to him afterwards and it all works out nicely. So yes,
in principle that's okay, but that נראה כמסייע, nireh kemesayeya, it's close
enough, it's hard enough it's pretty hard to distinguish that from a
case of an explicit deal. And if you allow one, you're going
to pretty soon be allowing the other. So they had to they
had to prevent that as well. But you're right, that is the
נראה nireh case. There's the real מסייע mesayeya where it's an explicit
deal and then there's the נראה nireh which is only a problem
because it looks enough like that. Once you might do it, Rifka,
with the sincerest of motives and it really was an honest volunteering
and an honest gift afterwards. But then I'm going to do it
because I see you can get away with it and I'm going
to do it and I'm going to really hire him. So we
have to allow prevent even the case that appears to be that,
not the case that are genuinely just genuine. Yes.
So the Torah is disapproving of welfare of work for welfare. It
really is. It's very... It is not our capitalistic values. That's right.
And also, you know what?
Well, wait, wait, wait, wait, I want to take it back. I
want to I'm taking this back.
Okay, first of
all we have a whole
סוגיא sugya because
no, you just
can't do it
from the מעשר עני, ma'aser ani, right? It rejects its master and
not the... Yeah, but he might have given, he might have given
it to other עניים.
aniyim. Look, we look,
look, look, in terms of that, clearly in the hierarchy of תורה
Torah values when it comes to צדקה, tzedakah, we say that if
somebody finds a job for somebody or hires somebody for a business
is better than somebody who gives straight charity because it maintains the
dignity and it makes the person self-sufficient and all of this. Here
we're talking about not the overarching is this a good thing to
give somebody a job. We are talking about the specific institution of
תרומות trumos and מעשרות maasros and so on, which are supposed to
be a freely given gift. Okay? The overarching institution, the general institution,
yes, better to give somebody a job than to give them just
a straight handout. All right. Now let's keep on going. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: You have violated the, you have desecrated
the institution. I know. ולהלן הכתוב אומר, Ulehalan hakatuv omer, regarding them
the verse says
שחתם ברית הלוי. shichatem bris haLevi. You have sort of
destroyed, corrupted, or whatever, the covenant of the לוי. Levi. By the
way, I will say, I understand that you're reacting more about the
poor, but the כהן Kohen and the לוי, Levi, I think you
understand that there, first of all, תרומה trumah probably more is like
a gift to God and the כהן Kohen more just representing God,
but by מעשר maaser certainly it, the verse says חלף עבודתם אשר
הם עובדים. chelef avodatam asher hem ovdim. The מעשר maaser is in
exchange for the service that the לויים Leviyim do, either in the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash or as teachers, they're also in the תורה
Torah they're teachers.
So there the problem is that it's supposed to be an exchange
for their general religious service, not for them working as helpers in
your threshing house. Okay? So there it really undermines the whole point
about what is their role and how you're acknowledging their role by
giving them the תרומות trumos and מעשרות. maasros. When you give תרומות
trumos and מעשרות, maasros, you're acknowledging them as the sort of religious
functionaries and they're being given this because of their religious service, and
when you're doing it because they're working in the threshing house, you're
giving it to them because they're farmhands. Okay? So I think you
can appreciate at least by the כהן Kohen and לוי Levi why
this is a problem. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואומר
את קדשי בני ישראל לא תחללו ולא תמותו. Ve'omer es kodshei bnei
Yisrael lo sechalelu velo samusu. You should not desecrate the sanctified things
of בני ישראל bnei Yisrael and you should not die. Now again,
it's not that you're desecrating the object as much as the institution.
מאי ואומר? Mai ve'omer? What is the second verse telling? וכי תימא
מיתה לא? Vechi teima misa lo? Okay, it's a bad thing, but
it's not like you're deserving of death. So תא שמע את קדשי
בני ישראל לא תחללו ולא תמותו. Ta shema es kodshei bnei Yisrael
lo sechalelu velo samusu. Okay, which is pretty heavy. תוספות Tosafos says
it doesn't really mean it. It's
never listed as some of the things that you're even חייב chayav
heavenly death for, but it is, we're saying it is as if.
וביקשו חכמים לקנסן וליזמינהו עלייהו תרומה משלם. Uvikshu chachamim lekansan uleizmineihu aleihu
trumah mishalem. And the rabbis wanted actually fine somebody who used this
תרומות trumos and מעשרות maasros as payment and say they would have
to give תרומות trumos and מעשרות maasros a second time all over
again if they did this because then it would be fully. Okay?
So I'm not exactly clear what
that means, but anyway, to say you've turned it into a fee,
into payment for services, so you have to now give a real
תרומה trumah and מעשר. maaser. ומפני מה לא קנסום? Umipnei mah lo
kensum? Why did they not fine them? דילמא אתי לאפרושי מן הפטור
על החיוב. Dilma asi le'afroshei min hapatur al hachiyuv. Because then you
will think that you have never really taken תרומות trumos and מעשרות
maasros although biblically you have, and then when you take the second
one, which is only rabbinic, you'll use that to exempt other grain
which is biblically obligated. So we didn't say take it a second
time because then it would make you think that it really was
a real obligation the second time and it could lead to other
problems. ובכולן יש בהם טובת הנאה לבעלים. Uvechulan yesh bahem tovas hana'ah
labaalim. So although you are not allowed to pay it, use it
as payment of services, you do have the benefit of deciding who
it gets to go to and that actually you can turn into
money in terms of who does it get to go to. What
does this mean? כיצד? Keitzad? How is this true? דף כז עמוד
א. Daf chaf zayin amud aleph. ישראל שהפריש תרומה מכריו. Yisrael shehifrish
trumah mikaryo.
An Israelite separated out תרומה trumah from his pile of grain and
now he has to find a כהן Kohen to give it to.
ומצא ישראל אחר, Umatza Yisrael acher, and another Israelite finds him. ואמר
לו, Ve'amar lo, and says to him: הילך סלע זה, Heilach sela
zeh, here, take this סלע, sela, just 20
bucks, ותנהו לבן בתי כהן. usneihu lven biti Kohen. And I have
a grandson who's a כהן. Kohen. I'm a ישראל, Yisrael, but I've
got a grandson who's a כהן Kohen because my daughter married a
כהן. Kohen. So I'll give you 20 bucks if you give it
to him. So you know what? מותר. Mutar. That's actually permissible because
then you are taking the money for your discretion of who to
give it to, but it's not like it's a payment of services.
And that is not a question of מסייע בבית הגרנות, mesayei beveit
hagranot, right? You are just taking money to, you have to decide
who to give it to and somebody's giving you a little bit
of a fee for your, or a gift.
Oh, this guy 20 bucks and then you give it to him.
Like, oh, the little 20 bucks that you owe me.
No, no, no, no, no. But the problematic case is the next
one. אם היה כהן לכהן אסור. Im hayah Kohen leKohen asur. However,
if I'm a כהן Kohen and I say to you, here's 20
bucks to give it to a כהן, Kohen, that is forbidden. Why?
Because if you're, because then if it's an exchange with a כהן,
Kohen, and here it's very interesting, even if the כהן Kohen giving
you the money is not the כהן Kohen receiving it, but it
looks basically like not just that he's paying you. for you, for
your discretion of who you want to give it to, it looks
like he's directly buying the actual תרומה, terumah, the actual תרומה terumah
itself. Like you understand? If I'm a כהן kohen and I gave,
if I'm a ישראל Yisrael and I give you twenty dollars and
you give it to my friend here the כהן, kohen, so why
did I give you the twenty dollars? So that you would make
a choice who to give it to. I didn't pay you the
twenty dollars, this grain is worth a hundred dollars. I didn't buy
the grain off you for a hundred dollars, I paid you twenty
dollars in order to influence your choice of who you give it
to. So there that's okay if I'm paying you for your choice,
I'm not paying you for the grain itself. But if I gave,
let's say it was a כהן, kohen, let's say it was straight
to me before we get to another guy. Here's twenty dollars, I'd
like you to choose to give it to me. Then it gets
much more confusing because then it doesn't necessarily just look like I'm
giving you the money to influence your choice. I gave you twenty
dollars, you gave me a hundred dollars of grain. It looks like
I bought the תרומה terumah off of you. Okay, right. Fact, exactly,
I bought the תרומה terumah off of you. So therefore, by extension,
although it's not the same, even if I'm a כהן kohen and
I give you twenty dollars to give it to my friend the
כהן, kohen, I know, don't touch it. I get it, I get
it. But that is like the near-ish. Okay. So what we are
concerned about is, and that is the line that's being drawn, is
you can do something to get some influence on somebody's decision who
to give it to, but you cannot do something that basically can
be interpreted, is or can be interpreted, as service or payment for
the actual תרומות ומעשרות terumos and maasros themselves. That undermines, it seems,
the institution of the תרומות ומעשרות. terumos and maasros. Okay. So
now we continue. ותני, vetani, ותני ברייתא, u’tni baraita, מאי טעמא לא
קאמר מתנות כהונה? mai ta'ama lo ka’amar matnos kehuna? So why did
outside ותני, vetani, excuse me, our
ברייתא, baraita, why did it mention מתנות כהונה matnos kehuna meaning just
one second let me just check
רש"י. Rashi. Oh right. So let's see.
We only mentioned תרומה terumah over here, right? תרומה terumah קריאה keriah
because the case over here...
right right. Why did it only mention תרומה? terumah? Thank you. When
it went to the טובת הנאה tovas hana'ah case, why did it
only mention תרומה? terumah? It started with cases about the בכור, bechor,
זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zero'a l'chayayim v'keiva, the מעשר עני. ma'aser ani. So
why when it got to paying somebody for making a decision did
it only give the example of מתנות... matnos... of תרומה? terumah? מאי
טעמא לא קאמר מתנות כהונה? mai ta'ama lo ka’amar matnos kehuna? Why
did it not give the example of the other מתנות כהונה matnos
kehuna like the בכור bechor and זרוע לחיים וקיבה? zero'a l'chayayim v'keiva?
אמר לך, amalacha, I'll tell you, תרומה דקדושת הגוף היא. terumah de’kdushas
haguf hi. Since תרומה terumah has intrinsic קדושה. kedushah. וכיון דלא מתחלא,
vekivan d’lo mitchallah, לא
אתי למטעי בה. lo asei limit’pei. Since the קדושה kedushah isn't transferred,
you will not come to be confused. I gave Michael twenty dollars,
he gave this תרומה terumah to my grandson the כהן. kohen. Okay,
nobody thinks that because of the twenty dollars the תרומה terumah lost
its קדושה. kedushah. They understand the twenty dollars was to influence his
decision. אבל
הני, aval hani, but the others, like בכור bechor which could have
a מום mum or even better the case of let's... of what
do you call it? Of like זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zero'a l'chayayim v'keiva,
כיון דקדושת דמים נינהו, kevan de’kedushas damim ninhu, it's basically a sanctity
of money and not of קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. I'll explain what
that means in a minute. אתי למטעי בהן. ati limit’pei bahen. You
might come to make a mistake and say דבר מתחלא דבר מתחלא
קדושתיה ארבע זוז. davar mitchala debar mitchala kedushasei arba zuz. That the
קדושה kedushah can be transferred to four זוז, zuz, as the סלע
sela example was four זוז. zuz. ואתי למנהג בה מנהג דחולין. ve’ati
liminhag bei minhag de’chullin. And you'll come to treat it as if
it's completely not sanctified. Now what does this mean exactly? First of
all, a בכור bechor has קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. A בכור bechor
is brought as a קרבן. korban. Okay. With a blemish however, it's
not exactly... it's not exactly קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf anymore. In a
way it is, but it's not exactly. So maybe it means the
case of like a בכור bechor with a blemish. But it seems
more what we're talking about is the זרוע לחיים וקיבה. zero'a l'chayayim
v'keiva. Except those don't have any קדושה. kedushah. The זרוע לחיים וקיבה,
zero'a l'chayayim v'keiva, if you remember it from חולין, Chullin, are gifts
to the כהן kohen from, you know, the arm and the mouth
area of the animal. They're without any קדושה kedushah but are given
to a כהן. kohen. So it's not even קדושת דמים. kedushas damim.
Meaning a בכור bechor is more than קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, זרוע
לחיים וקיבה zero'a l'chayayim v'keiva is not even... it's really no קדושה.
kedushah. So the גמרא Gemara here means it a little imprecisely. But
if you remember we had a fun time at the end of
חולין Chullin where it spoke about that even if the thing has
no קדושה, kedushah, there's a proper way of giving, there's a proper
way of receiving, right? When you eat it, you eat it in
a particular way. It says you eat it in a way like
it spoke about like, you know, dips in... dipped in mustard and
roasted. You know, a way that shows and then the גמרא Gemara
in the end and תוספות Tosafos said that's only if you don't
like it particularly any other way. But anyway, a way that shows
that you are sort of through the way it's given and through
the way it's received and eaten, it represents the fact that you
acknowledge the status of the כהן kohen and the significance of this
gift. So because of that, we might think though because... so it
has some status. It's not really קדושה, kedushah, but it has status
and it's supposed to be treated in a certain way. So we
might think that if I gave Michael four dollars for him to
give that to my friend the כהן kohen or to my grandson
the כהן, kohen, that we might think, 'Oh, well then that really
became like a type of a... now it's sort of like was
bought with that money.' And therefore now maybe he doesn't even have
to eat it in any special way. It's just complete חולין. chullin.
It no longer has the status... of gifts of כהונה kehuna and
doesn't have to be eaten in a particular way. And therefore that
might lead to a further degradation of the status of that object.
So therefore, interestingly, of gifts of כהונה kehuna and doesn't have to
be eaten in a particular way. And therefore that might lead to
a further degradation of the status of that object. So therefore, interestingly,
because it has less קדושה kedusha we don't allow this exchange. Another
way to just rephrase that is very simply. The whole problem here
is it should not look like I'm buying it, right? So that's
why we only let me do it if I'm giving them and
I'm not a כהן kohen and I'm giving to somebody else who
is a כהן, kohen, it doesn't look like I'm buying it. But
the more the thing itself is not in itself קדוש, kadosh, like
the זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zero'a lechayayim vekeiva, the more this deal can
look like I am purchasing it. And therefore, in that case, we
do not allow me to give to the butcher a little gift
that he can give it to somebody who is my pal and
my friend and so on. Okay, so the only thing we allow
therefore is we don't allow certainly an exchange of services, we don't
allow things that look like an exchange of services. We allow we
don't allow a כהן kohen to give money for the ישראל Yisrael
to give the תרומה truma to another כהן kohen certainly to himself
and not even to another כהן. kohen. That looks like he's purchasing
it. We only allow ישראל Yisrael to give money for the person
to give it to give the תרומה truma to a כהן. kohen.
That we'll say will look like money to influence a decision. That's
only bribery, that's not purchase. Okay so that actually is allowed but
we will only allow it by תרומה, truma, we will not allow
by זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zero'a lechayayim vekeiva, because then that will actually
seem like we have changed the status of the זרוע לחיים וקיבה
zero'a lechayayim vekeiva and will undermine their status once that exchange took
place. Charlie and then.
מעשר עני ma'aser ani doesn't have any physical sanctity.
So why could you not do this by מעשר עני ma'aser ani
give money to give it to a particular עני? ani? Yeah, right.
That's good question, maybe you can. You're right. That is completely חולין.
chulin. It doesn't even have the status of a particular status the
way it's eaten. So I don't know. That's good question, maybe you
can give some money to influence who you're going to give your
מעשר עני ma'aser ani to.
And back to the possible penalty for תרומה, truma, they could have
done it for מעשר עני ma'aser ani because all that would be
would be forcing someone to properly give additional
money to the poor.
One more time?
So they thought about fining to
give it again
fining and force them to give again the תרומה, truma, but none
of the reasons for not doing that for תרומה truma would apply
to מעשר עני. ma'aser ani.
Well no because by מעשר עני ma'aser ani there's a concern still
about שמא יפריש מן הפטור על החיוב, shema yafreish min hapatur al
hachiyuv, right? I have other grain that hasn't had מעשר עני ma'aser
ani taken, I take this a second time and therefore I think
I'm exempting the other grains as well.
So there's same concern that if I don't fully understand the status
I might come to misuse you know use it to exempt something
else, that's equally alive by מעשר עני. ma'aser ani. Oh okay. Yes.
So you're saying that like you know I can auction on eBay
like the right to you know no seriously you know like in
terms of modern modern times the right to you know you to
purchase my decision to give it to any כהן kohen and it
doesn't A either look like a purchase because that's what you're really
doing right or B that it doesn't look like it's undermining the
institution?
But only
if the ישראל Yisrael is paying the money because it's your because
it's I mean I understand like in the world we live in
that would basically be what you normally consider consider sort of graft
and bribery lite when you're supposed to like if you're supposed to
award a contract right and somebody so everybody's paying actually paid for
the services but then to pay the guy to make the decision
who gets the contract right that's that's exactly what the right inappropriate
the most inappropriate right. I understand you know here the point is
is that you are given complete discretion who to give it to
you know the תורה Torah doesn't say you have to give it
to the most deserving person you are given complete discretion. It is
interesting that חז"ל Chazal understand that you actually can offer that off
you know to be to sell that right. But again it's in
very limited cases and then the rich people always win and then
you know yeah I understand it's a real problem. All right let's
keep on going.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, תרומת חוץ
לארץ אין בה משום קונה מבית הגרנות. Trumas chutz la'aretz ein ba
mishum koneh mibeis hagranos. If it's תרומה truma from outside of Israel
that's only Rabbinic and since it's only Rabbinic we don't have any
of these problems and therefore you can use it to do this
payment for service.
You mean like ארם צובא Aram Tzova or something like that? What?
Well yeah there's a question about how many lands of חוץ לארץ
chutz la'aretz had the obligation of תרומות ומעשרות trumos uma'asros in the
משניות Mishnayos or whatever it talks about immediate areas it seems even
בבל, Bavel, Syria yeah well no Syria's a different category altogether but
even places that are not quasi קדושה kedusha but just surrounding lands
it sounds like it's even בבל. Bavel. תוספות Tosfos has a question
about whether it applies in like France and whatever and in the
end they say no it only applies in the lands that are
nearby Israel. Anyway so that's only Rabbinic and therefore we allow it.
רב חמא יהבליה לשמעיה. Rav Chama yeivlei leshama'ei. רב חמא Rav Chama
gave it so here are people that lived in בבל Bavel אמוראים
Amora'im who lived in בבל Bavel who did this exchange of service.
So רב חמא Rav Chama gave it to his
servant to might be תרומה truma it might also be זרוע לחיים
וקיבה zero'a lechayayim vekeiva okay which although that's maybe not so clear
because that might be דאורייתא d'Oraisa actually so let's leave it as
תרומה truma okay because that's the context. Okay so he gave his
תרומה truma to his servant basically as a pay as a payment
for service. אמר שמואל
*Amar Shmuel*, so now שמואל *Shmuel* said, תרומת חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz,
בטלה ברוב *Trumat chutz la'aretz betela berov*. Now that we're talking about
תרומה trumah *Truma* in ארץ *Eretz* out of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael,
*Eretz Yisrael*, we're going to talk about a whole list of leniencies
about תרומה trumah *Truma* out of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael*.
So number one is normally you need sixty or a hundred to
be to nullify תרומה trumah *Truma*, but the תרומה terumah, *Truma* of
חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz *chutz la'aretz* is בטל *battel* in a majority.
Not only is it בטל *battel* in a majority, as we're about
to read in the next line, you can proactively do that. So
let's take a look. רבה *Rabba*, רבה *Rabba* who was a כהן
kohen. *Kohen*, מבטל ברוב mevatel b'rov, *mevatel berov*, he would nullify it
in majority, ואכלה בימי טומאתו *ve'ocheilah bimei tum'aso*, and that would allow
him to eat it when he was טמא tamei *tamei*. Now רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says even if you're a ישראל *Yisrael*, you could be
מבטל ברוב *mevatel berov* and eat it and it's like there's no
תרומה terumah *Truma*. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* says that we only allowed you
to proactively be מבטל *mevatel*, normally you can never do this, אין
מבטלין איסור לכתחילה *ein mevatlin issur l'chatchila*. We don't allow you to
create ביטול *bittul*. But here we do, and תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafos* says
not for ישראל *Yisrael* to eat it, but for a כהן *Kohen*
to eat it if he's טמא tamei *tamei*. We allow you to
proactively create תרומה *Truma*. Now רבה *Rabba* was a כהן *Kohen*. רש"י
*Rashi* and תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* both point out that רבה *Rabba*, there's
other גמרות *Gemaros* that say that רבה *Rabba* was descended from בית
עלי *Beis Eli*. So who was, you know, the כהן *Kohen* in
the time of, you know, going way back, שמואל *Shmuel*. So therefore,
so therefore רבה *Rabba* had תרומה *Truma*, he was טמא tamei *tamei*,
so he was מבטל ברוב *mevatel berov*. It was in חוץ לארץ
chutz la'aretz *chutz la'aretz*.
רב Rav הונא בריה
דרב de-Rav יהושע *Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua*, now רב Rav הונא
*Rav Huna* the son of רב Rav, יהושע *Rav Yehoshua*, כי איסרמי
ליה חמרא דתרומה *ki isrami lei chamra de'truma*, when he, he was
also a כהן *Kohen*, and when he had תרומה *Truma* wine that
was given to him, הוה רמי תרי נטלי דחולין וחד נטלא דתרומה
*hava rami trei natlei de'chullin ve'chad natla de'truma*, he would take two
buckets or two of of חולין *chullin* and one of תרומה *Truma*,
so maybe he didn't do just a fifty-one percent majority, he did
a two-to-one mix, okay, two two unit you know, two units of
חולין *chullin* wine, one unit of תרומה *Truma* wine, so he would
proactively mix it up, ושקיל חד מכאן ושקיל ושקיל חד *ve'shakil chad
mikan
ve'shakil ve'shakil chad*, and then he would take out one, you know,
one bucket and drink that. And so he mixed up two-to-one, there's
a majority, he'd take out one bucket and he would say it's
בטל *battel* and therefore he would drink it even though he was
טמא tamei. *tamei*. מכאן ואילך *mikan ve'eilach*, after that first bucket, רמי
חד ושקיל חד *rami chad ve'shakil chad*. He put in one and
take out one. So meaning there would always be two left in
the two units left in the barrel, right, you get it? There
were two units of חולין *chullin*, one unit of תרומה *Truma*, mixed
it all together. Now, you could have said, okay, the majority is
חולין *chullin*, I'm going to drink it all. But he wanted to
be a little פרום *froomer*, so he said is, I'm only going
to take out one unit and then I'll replace it with another
unit. So that way, you're leaving two units in the barrel and
taking one unit out. So therefore you can assume that the majority
is left in the barrel, not only that, twice as much is
left in the barrel, we can assume that the all the תרומה
*Truma* was left in the barrel and what I took out was
the חולין *chullin*. Okay, so it was a פרום *froomer* way of
doing ביטול ברוב *bittul berov*, but it was still not that demanding.
And that allowed him to eat it even though he was טמא
tamei *tamei*. This is all because it's תרומת חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz,
*Trumat chutz la'aretz*, yes.
But by the second ladle, it now has the majority of תרומה
*Truma*.
No, if you deal with the actual proportions, everything actually has one-third
to two-thirds. No, he kept on replacing the one unit with חולין
*chullin*.
Oh, replacing it with חולין *chullin*.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, that was the way. Replacing it with חולין *chullin*.
Oh. No, no. So there was always going to be at least
a two-to-one ratio, if not better. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this. ואמר שמואל *V'amar Shmuel*, שמואל *Shmuel* said, תרומת
חוץ לארץ אוכל והולך ואחר כך מפריש *Trumat chutz la'aretz ochel ve'holeich
v'achar kach mafrish*. תרומת חוץ לארץ *Trumat chutz la'aretz* you could be
so lenient that you can eat the entire pile of grain and
leave over a tiny little bit at the end and after you're
totally done eating it, the stuff that's left over you'll make תרומה
*Truma*. Normally you have to make תרומה *Truma* proactively, I mean not
proactively, wrong word, initially, at the outset. Here you can make and
that allows the grain to be eaten. Here you only have to
make sure you give it eventually. You don't need to, but the
act of separating it which is really a principle that there is
not so much of a concept as טבל tevel, *tevel* of the
grain being forbidden until the תרומה *Truma* is taken. Even if you
take תרומה *Truma* at the end, you're okay. Okay, so a lot
of leniencies that it does not really have the full status of
תרומה *Truma* and the grain doesn't have the full status of טבל
*tevel* in the lands, yeah, Israel, yeah, I don't know how many
of them they were you know, there's still any serious Jewish communities,
okay. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, ואמר שמואל *V'amar
Shmuel*, שמואל *Shmuel* said, אין תרומת חוץ לארץ אסורה אלא במי שטומאה
יוצאה עליו מגופו *ein Trumat chutz la'aretz asura ella be'mi she'tuma yotzei
alav migufo*. Not only that, a כהן *Kohen* wants to eat תרומה
*Truma* in חוץ לארץ *chutz la'aretz*, normally if you're טמא tamei *tamei*
you can't eat תרומה *Truma* with any type of טומאה tumah *tuma*.
Here they said it's only about a טומאה tumah *tuma* that defines
you that will literally mean that the טומאה tumah *tuma* comes from
your body. What type of טומאה tumah, *tuma* comes from your body?
For a man it means a זב *zav*, an unnatural penile flow,
or בעל קרי *ba'al keri*, seminal emission. For a woman it means
a נדה *niddah* or a זבה *zavah*. Okay, those would be the
cases of blood flows either during the menstrual period or not during
the menstrual period. These are טמא tamei, *tamei*, yes, even טמא tamei
*tamei*. So those are טומאה יוצאה מגופו tumah yotzei migufo *tuma yotzei
migufo*. Those are seen to some degree to be more defining, not
necessarily the weightiest טומאה *tuma*, טומאת מת tumas meis. *tumas meis* is
the weightiest, but more defining of the person. They're about what, about
your your own state of, you know, your own personal physical state.
So therefore those are the ones that are the sort of most
inappropriate for תרומה *Truma* of חוץ לארץ *chutz la'aretz*, but anybody else,
no matter if כהן *Kohen* has other טומאה *tuma*, he can eat
this תרומה *Truma* of חוץ לארץ *chutz la'aretz*, which is amazing. You
can eat the תרומה *Truma*. even if you’re טמא tamei *tamei*, but
again, it’s all תרומה *Terumah* of חוץ לארץ *Chutz Laaretz*. There’s no
קדושה kedusha *Kedushah* for land outside of Israel, so the whole question
is what’s, you know, what type of status did the Rabbis give
it. You could understand they didn’t want to give it too weighty
a status because that would undermine the institution of the קדושה *Kedushah*
of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael*. So they have all of
these leniencies. It’s easy to create ביטול *Bittul*, you can actually give
it at the very end, meaning the grain isn’t really טבל *Tevel*.
And now we’re saying that you can even eat it when you’re
טמא *Tamei* as long as it’s not יוצא מגופו *Yotzei Migufo*, it
doesn’t define you personally.
Why have it to begin with?
Why having it to begin with could be that, that’s a good
question. One, it could be most probably one of two reasons. Like
one is to, because of Jews that are living nearby Israel, not
in Israel itself, you know, it still helps sort of support them,
so as a sort of almost like a social program for the
כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* and לויים *Levi'im*. And the other probably is just,
you know, as with anything, we, it’s a protect, you’re right, like
I was going to say sort of like to protect the idea
of the דאורייתא *D'oraisa* in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael*, you
want to do it even outside. But here we’re seeing that by
adding to it, it could undermine the original institution, so it’s trying
to strike that balance. But you make a good point because naturally
we would have thought, well why do you want to do it?
Well, you know, to protect the institution of תרומה *Terumah* in Israel,
you want to even extend its reach even beyond. But here we’re
seeing, you know, that you actually, they made it very lenient because
the very extension could undermine the significance of Israel itself. So it’s
definitely a tightrope here. Okay.
Do they have to take תרומה *Terumah* from Israel
outside for Israel? No, they don’t.
So you’d never confuse them. Right. I mean, there are certain cases,
but as a general rule, no. Okay. אמר שמואל *Amar Shmuel*, אין
תרומה *ein Terumah*, okay, אלא מי שטומאה יוצאה מגופו *ella mi shetuma
yotzei migufo*. והני מילי באכילה *V'hani milei b'achila*, and even that is
only when it comes to eating it. אבל בנגיעה *Aval b'negi'ah*, when
it comes to touching תרומה *Terumah*, לית לן בה *leis lan bah*,
even if, even the person that has a, that is טומאה *Tumah*
because of something that happened to their body can touch תרומה *Terumah*.
So the only restriction of תרומה *Terumah* and טומאה *Tumah* of תרומת
חוץ לארץ *Trumas Chutz Laaretz* and טומאה *Tumah* is eating by a
person who has טומאה יוצאה מגופו tumah yotzei migufo, *Tumah Yotzei Migufo*.
And now we’re going to have a nice example of that. אמר
אבינא *Amar Avina*, הלכך *hilkach*, therefore, let me give you an example.
נדה קוצה חלה challah. *Nidda kotza challah*, if a woman is a
נדה *Nidda* who’s making חלה Challah *Challah*, so she’s טומאה יוצאה מגופו
tumah yotzei migufo. *Tumah Yotzei Migufo*, right, it’s about her own personal
state, the טומאה *Tumah*. She can’t eat the תרומה *Terumah* even if
she’s married to a כהן *Kohen*, but she can touch it. So
she can be kneading dough, separating out חלה *Challah*. חלה *Challah* is
a type of a תרומה *Terumah* in חוץ לארץ *Chutz Laaretz*. Okay,
it’s okay for her to touch it. ואכלה כהן קטן *V'ochla kohen
katan*, and who’s going to eat it? She’ll feed it to her
son. Her son who’s a כהן *Kohen*, let’s say she’s married to
a כהן *Kohen*, she can’t eat it although she’s married to a
כהן *Kohen* because she has טומאה יוצאה מגופו tumah yotzei migufo. *Tumah
Yotzei Migufo*. She can touch it, feed it to her son. Why
feed it to her son? Because her son probably doesn’t have, what
type of טומאה יוצאה מגופו *Tumah Yotzei Migufo* would a man have?
Most likely seminal emission. If her son is a minor and he’s
not yet of age, so we don’t have to worry about that.
So therefore feed it to her son. Now, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* says
maybe we just mentioned feeding it to her son because maybe the
amount you give for חלה *Challah* when it’s חלת חוץ לארץ *Challas
Chutz Laaretz* is only a tiny amount. It raises an interesting question
that there are some that say, although the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* makes
it sound that you just can’t have the טומאה *Tumah*, so if
a man had that or a woman had that, they go to
the מקוה mikvah *Mikvah* and then they can eat it. But because
it gives this example about giving it to a minor child, some
want to say that maybe it should only be given to somebody
who cannot, is not yet of the age that it could have
ever occurred yet that they would have had the טומאה יוצאה מגופו
*Tumah Yotzei Migufo*. But that’s a big stretch and definitely not what’s
assumed. It’s just assumed that this is an example. Okay. So again,
it’s only limited in eating and only by somebody who is טומאה
יוצאה מגופו *Tumah Yotzei Migufo*.
Now, where were we? ואכלה כהן קטן *V'ochla kohen katan*. ואי ליכא
כהן קטן *V'ee lekka kohen katan*, that if you don’t have a
כהן *Kohen* who’s a minor, and that’s why it sounded like maybe
it means דוקא *davka* minor. Who needs a כהן קטן *kohen katan*
minor? Just giving it to somebody who’s not טמא *tamei* right now,
who had, you know, a נדה *Nidda* or a בעל קרי *ba'al
keri* who went to the מקוה mikvah *Mikvah*. Why you need דוקא
*davka* minor? But no, it says if there’s no minor around, שקלה
לריש מאסא *shakla l'reish masa*, let her put it at the top
of like a, of a stick essentially, some type of a thing
used in the oven, ושדי בתנורא *v'shadi b'tanura*, and throw it in
the oven, burn it. Okay, because there are חלות challahs, *Challahs*, when
we take חלה *Challah* in חוץ לארץ *Chutz Laaretz*, we take a
little bit and, right, people know, you put this in the oven
and you burn it because you can’t eat it because you’re טמא
*tamei*.
So you can’t give it to a child who’s a little girl,
just a boy?
You could. No, you could. Yeah, you could. Okay. Yeah, as long
as they’re כהן *Kohen*, right. Okay. והדר *V'hadar*, now if you’re going
to burn that one because there’s nobody available to eat it given
the טומאה *Tumah* restriction, מפרשה חלה אחריתי *mefarsha challah achrisi*, separate out
another חלה *Challah*, כי היכי דלא תשתכח תורת חלה *k'heichi d'lo tishtakkach
toras challah*, so you don’t forget the idea of חלה *Challah*, which
is that it’s supposed to be eaten by a כהן *Kohen*, ואכלה
כהן גדול *v'ochla kohen gadol*, and then an adult כהן *Kohen* can
eat it. Okay, so that’s the whole idea of separating out two
חלות challahs *Challahs*. There’s a very big תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* here that
talks about the whole concept of two חלות challahs *Challahs* because the,
there are two degrees as we’ve been talking, mentioning in passing, of
what it means חוץ לארץ *Chutz Laaretz*, right? We don’t take תרומות
ומעשרות *Trumos and Ma'asros* even if we happen to be a farmer
in Idaho or something,
you know, we don’t take תרומה *Terumah* outside of the land immediately
near Israel, but what we do take is
חלה *Challah*, right, because חלה *Challah*... So therefore there are different degrees
of two חלות. challahs In Israel itself you only take one חלה.
In the land sort of, you know, sort of a certain areas
of Israel or right near it or whatever, you take two חלות,
but there the first one is the עיקר, ikar, but and the
second one anyway so but what do you do? I don't you
know what? It's too much. I'm not going to go into it
now. We're behind. But I wanted to say there are two חלות
in the land right around Israel and then there's two חלות for
us in Syria's חוצה לארץ, chutza'aretz, the exact status of those two
חלות are different whether it's the lands right near Israel or it's
further חוצה. chutza. But yes, so but here we take one and
we burn it and well we could eat it if there's no
טומאה problem. If there is a טומאה problem you burn it and
the other little bit else you take and it's eaten by a
כהן. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara if you want some other
time we can talk about הלכות חלה בזמן הזה. hilchos challah bizman
hazeh. Okay.
Okay. רב נחמן ורב עמרם ורמי בר חמא הוו קאזלי Rav Nachman
v'Rav Amram v'Rami bar Chama hava ka'azlei so Rav Nachman and where
are we? And Rav Amram and Rav Rami bar Chama were going
בארבא בבוט. b'arba b'vut. סליק רב עמרם לפנויי. Selik Rav Amram l'fanuyei.
So Rav Amram had to remove, you know, excuse himself to go
to the bathroom. אתאי ההיא איתתא, Asai hahi itata, a certain woman
came, עלתה קמייהו, alsah kama'ihu, came to these two rabbis that were
there. אמרה להו, Amrah lehu, she says to them, טמא מת מהו
שיטבול ויאכל תרומת חוצה לארץ? Tmei meis mahu sheyitbol v'yochal trumas chutza'aretz?
If somebody is טמא because of contact with the dead, can they
go to a מקוה mikvah and eat תרומה of חוצה לארץ? chutza'aretz?
Now that's a little funny because what good is going to a
מקוה mikvah if you haven't had the whole process of purification of
the ashes of פרה אדומה? parah adumah? Okay, so this was the
question. Now we've already seen that if you're טמא as long as
you don't have טומאה יוצאה מגופו you can eat תרומת חוצה לארץ.
trumas chutza'aretz. So let's see what they answer. אמר ליה רב נחמן
לרמי בר חמא, Amar lei Rav Nachman l'Rami bar Chama, so Rav
Nachman turned to Rami bar Chama, these are the two rabbis standing
there, the woman's asking them a question. וכי הזאה יש לנו? V'chi
haza'ah yesh lanu? Do we have sprinkling of the ashes of פרה
אדומה? parah adumah? So therefore since we don't have the sprinkling of
the ashes of פרה אדומה, parah adumah, if we allow people to
eat it anyway, right, we allow people to eat תרומת חוצה לארץ
trumas chutza'aretz anyway, then you don't then after the question was after
you've gone to the מקוה mikvah? normally you're not טהור tahor until
nightfall. So she wanted to know somebody went to the מקוה mikvah
and it hasn't been nightfall yet, can they eat תרומת חוצה לארץ?
trumas chutza'aretz? So he said look, we don't have, you're not really
going to become pure from your טומאת מת. We don't have sprinkling
of the ashes of פרה אדומה. parah adumah. So once that's true,
who needs you to wait for nightfall? Actually who needs you to
go to the מקוה? mikvah Okay, so who needs you to wait
for nightfall? Okay, so that's what he said. אמר ליה רמי בר
חמא, Amar lei Rami bar Chama, so Rami bar Chama said back
to him, וליחוש ליה לסבא, v'leichush lei l'saba, aren't you concerned about
the elder, meaning who was it? Rav Amram went to the bathroom.
Let's not give a ruling yet, let's wait till רב עמרם Rav
Amram comes back, let's hear his opinion.
אדהכי אתא רב עמרם, Ad'hachi asa Rav Amram, so while they were
talking Rav Amram returned. אמר להו, Amar lehu, he said to them,
הכי אמר רב, hachi amar Rav, here's what Rav says, טמא מת
טובל ואוכל בתרומת חוצה לארץ. tmei meis tovel v'ochel b'trumas chutza'aretz. טמא
מת Tmei meis goes to the מקוה mikvah and eats in תרומת
חוצה לארץ trumas chutza'aretz without waiting for night. Okay, so there you
go, you don't have to wait for night. One minute, one minute.
And then the גמרא Gemara. says, ולית הלכתא כוותיה, v'leis hilchasa k'vaseih,
says the גמרא, Gemara but we don't rule that way. ואמר מר
זוטרא משמיה דרב ששת, V'amar Mar Zutra mishmei d'Rav Sheshes, טמא שרץ
טובל ואוכל בתרומת חוצה לארץ. tmei sheretz tovel v'ochel b'trumas chutza'aretz. If
you're טמא because you touched a שרץ, sheretz, you go to the
מקוה mikvah and you and you eat from תרומת חוצה לארץ. trumas
chutza'aretz. ולית הלכתא כוותיה. V'leis hilchasa k'vaseih. Now we don't rule that
way. Now which way don't we rule that way? You could say
we don't rule that way and you have to wait for nightfall,
or we don't rule that way and Michael, who has to go
to the מקוה mikvah. to begin with? Right, if you're not טומאה
יוצאה מגופו, what we said before, you don't even have to go
to the מקוה mikvah, to begin with. So that's what תוספות Tosafot
says. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot ולית הלכתא כוותיה בהא דמטריח
טבילה. v'leis hilchasa k'vaseih b'ha d'matriach tvilah. אלא אפילו טבילה לא בעי,
Ella afilu tvilah lo ba'ei, you don't even have to go to
the מקוה. But he says from רש"י it sounds a little bit
like ולית הלכתא v'leis hilchasa and you have to wait till nightfall,
but that's not true. So תוספות Tosafot. making this discussion consistent with
the earlier one, saying when it comes to this whole big digression,
if you remember we got to because we talked about selling the
תרומה and תרומה for services and says it doesn't apply for תרומת
חוצה לארץ. trumas chutza'aretz. So we listed a whole string of leniencies
of תרומת חוצה לארץ. trumas chutza'aretz. It basically you can be מבטל
ברוב, you can give it at the end so it doesn't make
טבל, and here is the big one that's undermining its קדושה status.
You can eat it and touch it when you're טמא. The only
restriction is טומאה יוצאה מגופו. In that type of a case you
can't eat it. But anything else you can. And the way תוספות
understands the conclusion, you don't even have to go to the מקוה,
even though we're טמאי מת. tmei meis. All of that is okay,
just don't eat it when you're טומאה יוצאה מגופו. חלה is interesting,
that whole discussion about sounds like דפקא קטן, dafka katan, which is
a little funny, spoke about if there's nobody around to eat it
you burn it and then you give another one. שתי חלות, Shtei
challahs, that's a whole big discussion about שתי חלות בזמן הזה shtei
challahs bizman hazeh outside ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael closer to ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and so on, which we're not going to get to.
I will just say one final thing also, this view of תוספות
וכי הזאה יש לנו בזמן הזה, Tosafos v'chi haza'ah yesh lanu bizman
hazeh, interestingly most of this is not even about our topic. He
uses it as an opportunity to discuss his interpretation of some משניות
mishnayos and you know in זרעים Zeraim and so on. But the
point that I did want to bring out was that he actually
chooses to read the גמרא Gemara. not like they did not have
ashes of פרה אדומה, parah adumah, which is how you would normally
read the גמרא. Who has ashes of פרה אדומה parah adumah nowadays?
He actually chooses to read the גמרא as in, we're in חוץ
לארץ, who the heck ever thought that we have to go to
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to get the ashes of פרה אדומה parah
adumah sprinkled on us before we could eat the תרומה של חוץ
לארץ? terumah shel chutz la'aretz? And then there would be no point
of this whole institution. And every time you would walk back out
into חוץ לארץ to eat your תרומה, you would become טמא again.
So תוספות chooses to read it that they actually did have the
ashes of פרה אדומה parah adumah in ארץ ישראל, but they were
just saying it's crazy to think that we're required to do that.
Okay, but that is certainly not the פשט pshat of the גמרא.
Yes?
This woman who's asking the question, they're on a boat. So she's...
no one can go to the מקווה mikveh on the boat anyway,
so it's like a theoretical question.
On the sea, presumably.
Right. She can engage them and this question's really...
that's what it certainly seems to be. She's together with them. That
is definitely what it seems from the context, absolutely. Yes. Okay, yeah.
And the אמוראי, Amorai, there's the concept that the
lands outside of ארץ ישראל are טמא
and...
what? The lands... yes, so the lands, that's part of it, that
the land of ארץ ישראל is outside is טמא, וטומאת ארץ העמים,
ve'tumat eretz ha'amim, and that's part of this as well, meaning to
some degree you have to allow people טמא to eat תרומה in
חוץ לארץ because they're always considered טמא anyway in חוץ לארץ, which
is pretty much how תוספות reads the answer וכי אזא יש אנו
בזמן הזה? v'chi aza yesh anu bizman hazeh? Which means, you know,
what are you going to do? You're going to go back to
ארץ ישראל and become טהור? tahor? So what? As soon as you
step out, you're going to be dealing with טומאה again. So that's
pretty much how תוספות reads that and that's why to restrict טומאה,
we can only restrict it to the case of eating and only
טומאה יוצאת מגופו. tumah yotzet migufo. Okay, so that was a very
fascinating digression. Let's do a little bit more. בכור נאכל שנה בשנה.
bechor ne'echal shana beshana. So בכור, bechor, now that we're done with
raising it, we say that the בכור bechor should be eaten within
the year of its birth, whether brought as a קרבן korban or
whether eaten as a במה. bamah. Now again, to be clear, that
does not mean like the תורה Torah says some type of animals
as קרבנות korbanot have to be less than a year old. That,
when that happens, then if the animal becomes more than a year
old, then it is a פסול קרבן pasul korban because it's one
of the criteria, the same male, female, sheep or cow or goat.
Okay, one of the criteria is the age of the animal. That's
not, the תורה Torah never says the בכור bechor has to be
a certain age. It's not talking about the קרבן korban being invalid,
it's talking about your personal obligation to bring it or eat it,
you should do it within the year. If you were negligent, you
can still do it after the year, but you have an obligation
to do it within the year. So let's take a look. מדקאמר
נולד בו מום בתוך שנתו, mideka'amar nolad bo mum betoch shnato, since
it said and since it's going to deal with the case if
it had a blemish during its first year, and we'll talk about
that tomorrow, but here we're emphasizing the possessive: its year, its first
year. למימרא, lemeimra, that seems to say דלשנה דידיה מנינן. delishana didei
maninan. It's not by a calendrical year that we say bring it
within the year, but it's within its own year, bring it within
its first year. עברת שנה לפסול בבכור? avrat shana lipsoyl bevechor? Right,
so we know, we do not. We say that bring it before
its first birthday, that's what we're saying, not by a calendrical year.
Okay, מנהני מילי, minhani mili, where do you get this from? That,
A, that you do it, you're supposed to do it every year,
that we know שנה בשנה, shana beshana, but how do you know
its year? דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב דאמר קרא, da'mar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav d'amar kra, the verse says לפני ה' אלוהיך תאכלנו שנה
בשנה, lifnei Hashem elokecha tochelenu shana beshana, eat it before God year
by year. איזו שנה שנכנסת בחברתה, eizu shana shenichneset bachaverta, reading it
שנה בשנה, shana beshana, one year into a year. איזו שנה שנכנסת
בחברתה, eizu shana shenichneset bachaverta, what's a year that goes into another
year? הוי אומר שנה של בכור. hevei omer shana shel bechor. It
must be its birthday, meaning if you look on the calendar,
1999 doesn't go to 2000, and 2000 doesn't go to 2001. When
one ends, the other begins. But if you look at my birthday,
so my birthday does go, my year does go in from one
year to the next, right? It inter-it goes into the next calendrical
year. So how do you know it's the year of the sheep?
Because the year of the sheep is a year that goes into
a year, goes into from one calendar year to the next. Okay,
so דבי רב תנא, debei Rav tana, that's what רב Rav said.
The ישיבה yeshiva of רב had a different דרשה. drasha. שנה בשנה,
shana beshana, year by year, יום אחד בשנה זו ויום אחד בשנה
זו, yom echad beshana zu veyom echad beshana zo, not to tell
me the question about its own birthday, its year, tell me a
different הלכה, halacha, that you can eat this בכור bechor in two
years, in two calendrical years as a קרבן. korban. How could that
be? Well, if you brought it ערב ראש השנה, erev Rosh Hashanah,
then you eat it one day from the previous year and one
day from the next year, you're eating it in two different calendrical
years. What does this teach you? It teaches you a new הלכה.
halacha. לימד על הבכור שנאכל לשני ימים ולילה אחד. limed al habechor
shene'echal lishnei yamim velaylah echad. We don't know if it's brought as
a קרבן korban how long can you eat it. Some קרבנות korbanot
are eaten just for one day, some like שלמים shlamim are eaten
for two days. So the דרשה drasha of שנה בשנה shana beshana
that it's possible to eat the בכור bechor in two different years
teaches me that it's eaten for two days and I can bring
it on ערב ראש השנה erev Rosh Hashanah and eat it during
ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So דבי רב מנא להו? debei Rav mana
lehu? So if that's what דבי רב debei Rav is doing with
this דרשה drasha of שנה בשנה, shana beshana, where do they know
that you go by the sheep's own year to tell me when
you're supposed to bring it by? ילפי מקדשים, yalpi mikodshim, they learn
it from קדשים. kodshim. Okay, so I'm sorry, did I skip a
line?
Yeah, ילפי מקדשים, yalpi mikodshim, they learn it from קרבנות. korbanot. וקדשים
גופייהו מנא להו? vekodshim gufeihu mana lehu? That how do you know
other קרבנות korbanot are supposed to be brought within the year? So
אמר רב אחא בר יעקב אמר קרא, amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov
amar kra, the verse says כבש בן שנתו, keves ben shnato, that
you should bring a sheep within its year, possessive, as a קרבן.
korban. שנתו שלו ולא שנה של מנין עולם. shnato shelo velo shana
shel minyan olam. It's within its first year, not going by the
calendar. The calendar year. Now again, there is a difference because by
the sheep, like when it says כבש בן שנתו לעולה, keves ben
shnato le'olah, if it is more than a year old, then it
is a פסול קרבן. pasul korban. By the בכור, bechor, if it's
more than a year old it's not פסול, pasul, it's just that
you were supposed to bring it within that time. Okay?
Not a sheep, it's a lamb if it's before...
lamb, thank you, lamb. So but what we are learning is not
to invalidate the קרבן, korban, what we are learning is the idea
that... the idea that it's measured by its birthday and not by
the calendar. The רב, that's how the דרב knows the idea of
its year. נאכל לשני ימים ולילה אחד מנלה? ne'echal lishnei yamim velaylah
echad minalei? Where does רב learn the other הלכה, halacha, that it's
eaten for two days and the intervening night? נפקא ליה מבשרם יהיה
לך Nafka lei mibersaram yihyeh lach when the תורה Torah speaks about
the בכור bechor to the כהנים it says the flesh of the
בכור bechor will be for you, כחזה התנופה וכשוק הימין, ke-chazeh hatenufah
uche-shok hayamin, just like the gift from the שלמים, shelamim, the breast
and the thigh of the שלמים. shelamim. The תורה Torah equates the
בכור bechor to the breast and the thigh of a שלמים. shelamim.
Well, a שלמים shelamim is eaten for two days, so it's actually
a very straightforward link. היקישו הכתוב לחזה ושוק של שלמים, Hikisho hakatuv
le-chazeh veshok she-shelamim, it links it to the breast and the thigh
of the שלמים. shelamim. מה להלן לשני ימים ולילה אחד, Ma halan
lishnei yamim velaylah echad, the same way that is the שלמים shelamim
is the classic קרבן korban that's eaten for two days and the
intervening night, אף כאן לשני ימים ולילה אחד, af kan lishnei yamim
velaylah echad, here too as well. So just read one more sentence.
Look at that, you thought we weren't going to get through the
דף daf today. Thank God for the big תוספות. Okay, so if
that's so obvious, the verse links it to a שלמים, shelamim, why
do you have to learn it from שנה בשנה? shanah beshanah? ואידך,
Ve'idach, the other would say back, אי מהתם איכא למימר כחזה ושוק
של תודה. imei hatam ikka lemeimar ke-chazeh veshok she-todah. I could have
thought that like the thigh and the breast of a תודה, todah,
which is only one day, which is a subset of שלמים, shelamim,
I would not necessarily have linked it to the שלמים. shelamim. ואידך,
Ve'idach, so what's the response back? אמר קרא לך יהיה, Amar kra
lach yihyeh, it will be for you, הוסיף לך הכתוב הוויה אחרת
hosif lach hakatuv havayah acheret at the בכור, bechor, the תורה Torah
is giving you an extra ownership of the בכור, bechor, so therefore
it means not just one day but two days. Okay, and then
we will pick up with this, we'll wrap this up tomorrow and
go further.